<section number="20A-19-103"><effdate>8/25/2025</effdate><histories><history>Enacted by Statewide Initiative -- Proposition 4, Nov. 6, 2018</history><modyear>2018</modyear></histories><technotes>On March 28, 2020, S.B. 200 repealed Title 20A, Chapter 19. On August 25, 2025, the district court voided S.B. 200 in League of Women Voters, et al. v. Utah State Legislature, et al. and reinstated Title 20A, Chapter 19. Litigation is ongoing.</technotes><catchline>Redistricting Standards and Requirements.</catchline><subsection number="20A-19-103(1)">
This Section establishes redistricting standards and requirements applicable to the Legislature and to the Utah Independent Redistricting Commission.</subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(2)">
The Legislature and the Commission shall abide by the following redistricting standards to the greatest extent practicable and in the following order of priority:
<subsection number="20A-19-103(2)(a)">
adhering to the Constitution of the United States and federal laws, such as the Voting Rights Act, 52 U.S.C. Secs. 10101 through 10702, including, to the extent required, achieving equal population among districts using the most recent national decennial enumeration made by the authority of the United States;</subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(2)(b)">
minimizing the division of municipalities and counties across multiple districts, giving first priority to minimizing the division of municipalities and second priority to minimizing the division of counties;</subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(2)(c)">
creating districts that are geographically compact;</subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(2)(d)">
creating districts that are contiguous and that allow for the ease of transportation throughout the district;</subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(2)(e)">
preserving traditional neighborhoods and local communities of interest;</subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(2)(f)">
following natural and geographic features, boundaries, and barriers; and</subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(2)(g)">
maximizing boundary agreement among different types of districts.</subsection></subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(3)">
The Legislature and the Commission may not divide districts in a manner that purposefully or unduly favors or disfavors any incumbent elected official, candidate or prospective candidate for elective office, or any political party.</subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(4)">
The Legislature and the Commission shall use judicial standards and the best available data and scientific and statistical methods, including measures of partisan symmetry, to assess whether a proposed redistricting plan abides by and conforms to the redistricting standards contained in this Section, including the restrictions contained in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="20A-19-103(3)" start="0">(3)</xref>.</subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(5)">
Partisan political data and information, such as partisan election results, voting records, political party affiliation information, and residential addresses of incumbent elected officials and candidates or prospective candidates for elective office, may not be considered by the Legislature or by the Commission, except as permitted under Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="20A-19-103(4)" start="0">(4)</xref>.</subsection><subsection number="20A-19-103(6)">
The Legislature and the Commission shall make computer software and information and data concerning proposed redistricting plans reasonably available to the public so that the public has a meaningful opportunity to review redistricting plans and to conduct the assessments described in Subsection <xref depth="4" refnumber="20A-19-103(4)" start="0">(4)</xref>.</subsection></section>